Guide to the Flora Stieglitz Straus Collection of Stieglitz Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Addition (2005): Autochromes, 1915; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  The series contains five autochromes and their diascope viewers. Three photographs are of Flora Stieglitz Straus, with one each of her husband Hugh Grant Straus (1890-1961), and her maternal grandmother Jacobina Staerk Stieffel; they were made around 1915 by Nathan Straus Jr. (1889-1961), the brother of Hugh Straus. The diascopes are leather-covered transparency viewing devices patented in 1908 by the New York manufacturer L. A. Dubernet; each holder has a mirror on the back of a folding bellows which allows light to reflect back through the autochrome.
  Color reference prints of the five portraits are filed in the front of box 14.
  - Stieffel, Jacobina Staerk, circa 1915 (Box 13, Folder 185)
  - Straus, Hugh Grant, circa 1915 (Box 13, Folder 186)
  - Straus, Flora Stieglitz, circa 1915 (Box 13, Folder 187)
  - Straus, Flora Stieglitz, circa 1915 (Box 13, Folder 188)
  - Straus, Flora Stieglitz, circa 1915 (Box 13, Folder 189)
  - Diascope viewer, circa 1915 (Box 14, Folder 190)
  - Diascope viewer, circa 1915 (Box 14, Folder 191)
  - Diascope viewer, circa 1915 (Box 14, Folder 192)
  - Diascope viewer, circa 1915 (Box 14, Folder 193)
  - Number not used (Box 14, Folder 194)
- Addition (2008): Manuscripts, Photographs, Ephemera, 1860-1945; Series VII; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  The series contains a variety of letters and personal papers, photographs, and friendship albums. The first subseries, Manuscripts, includes a series of letters written by Alfred Stieglitz while a he was student in Germany, other letters written to Edward Stieglitz by family and friends, a set of hotel receipts documenting the Stieglitz family's travels in Germany and Switzerland in 1866, and invoices for household expenditures in Lake George and furnishings for their home in New York. It also holds friendship volumes kept by two of the Stieglitz sisters, Agnes and Selma, which were inscribed and drawn in by their friends and family members in Europe and America, including the artists Fedor Encke, Moses Jacob Ezekiel, Wilhelm Hasemann, and Otto Rauth. Also present are two partial diaries kept by Edward Stieglitz and his granddaughter Katherine ("Kitty") Stieglitz Stearns.
  Photographs is arranged under the headings of Albums, Individuals, Groups, and Miscellaneous. There are three photograph albums which hold snapshot-quality images of the Stieglitz family at home and at play in Europe and New York City (Manhattan and Queens), and at Lake George. Many of the images in box 17 are duplicated in other series in this collection, as well as in the Stieglitz/O'Keeffe Archive (YCAL MSS 85). Ephemera holds theatre handbills from performances in Germany in 1866.
  Organized into three subseries: Manuscripts; Photographs; and Ephemera.
  - Manuscripts
    - Engelhard, Agnes Stieglitz, friendship album, 1884-1896 (Box 15, Folder 195)
      Contains sentimental prose and poetry, and with drawings and watercolors by Fedor Encke, Wilhelm Hasemann, Otto Rauth, and Edward Stieglitz; signers are friends and family in Weimar, Berlin, Mittenwald, Vienna, New York City, and Lake George, NY; includes silhouette portrait of Alfred Stieglitz dated January 27, 1885.
    - Schubart, Selma Stieglitz, friendship album, 1885-1901 (Box 15, Folder 196)
      Purchased in Munich, cover gold-stamped "Sellie;" contains sentimental prose and poetry, drawings and watercolors, one photograph (by Alfred Stieglitz) and one etching; inscribed by friends and family in Munich, Rome, New York City, and Lake George, NY, and include Fedor Encke, Moses Ezekiel, and Alfred Stieglitz.
    - Stieglitz, Alfred
      - Letters to Stieglitz family, 1873-1880 (Box 15, Folder 197)
      - Letters to Stieglitz family, 1888-1895 (Box 15, Folder 198)
    - Stieglitz, Edward
      Arranged in chronological order
      - Letter from Sigmund Stieglitz, 1860 May 25 (Box 15, Folder 199)
      - Draft notice, 1864 Jul 13 (Box 15, Folder 200)
      - Invoices for family visits to hotels in Germany and Switzerland, 1866 (Box 15, Folder 201)
      - List of annual sales of leading dry goods houses in New York" [Hahlo & Stieglitz in second column], 1869 May 1 (Box 15, Folder 202)
      - Invoice for home furnishings, New York, 1871 Jan 26 (Box 15, Folder 203)
      - Letters from Hedwig Stieglitz, 1872 (Box 15, Folder 204)
      - Invoices for food and dry goods, Lake George, NY, 1878-1880 (Box 15, Folder 205)
      - Letter from Henry Wallach, 1880 Sep 18 (Box 15, Folder 206)
      - Travel diary, 1881, 1885 (Box 15, Folder 207)
        Covers trips to Europe (1881 Jun-Dec) and Rome (1885 Feb)
    - Stearns, Katherine ("Kitty") Stieglitz, diary, 1912 Jan-Jun (Box 15, Folder 208)
  - Photographs
    Arranged under four headings: Albums; Individuals; Groups; and Miscellaneous
    - Albums
      - Stieglitz family, 1896-1901 (Box 16, Folder 209)
        Snapshots of Stieglitz family members at Oaklawn, Edgemere (Queens, NY), and Manhattan; train stations and train tracks between Lake George and Albany
      - Stieglitz family, circa 1901 (Box 16, Folder 210)
        Small cropped snapshots of family members at Oaklawn, Saratoga, New York City, Prospect Mountain, and Far Rockaway (Queens, NY); many beach bathing, boating, golfing, and bicycling scenes; many photos of dogs, including Drew.
      - Stieglitz family, circa 1901-1906 (Box 16, Folder 211)
        Photographs of family members; buildings and people in Germany; scenes at Oaklawn; some interiors (perhaps in New York City); many are portraits of Stieglitz family children; possible portrait of the artist Wilhelm Hasemann; many taken by Alfred Stieglitz and Edward Steichen.
    - Individuals
      Arranged in alphabetical order
      - Cook, Mabel, circa 1890 (Box 17, Folder 212)
      - Davidson, Elizabeth Stieglitz, 1907 (Box 17, Folder 213)
      - Engelhard, Agnes Stieglitz, circa 1910 (Box 17, Folder 214)
      - Engelhard family (individual portraits), undated (Box 17, Folder 215)
      - Kuhn, Hedwig Stieglitz, 1896 (Box 17, Folder 216)
      - Obermeyer, Joseph, circa 1910 (Box 17, Folder 217)
      - Schubart, Selma Stieglitz, 1891-1914 (Box 17, Folder 218)
      - Schubart, William Howard, 1892, 1905 (Box 17, Folder 219)
        Includes gravure print portrait
      - Stearns, Katherine ("Kitty") Stieglitz, circa 1899 (Box 17, Folder 220)
      - Stieglitz, Alfred, circa 1866-1885 (Box 17, Folder 221)
      - Stieglitz, Edward, circa 1890, circa 1905 (Box 17, Folder 222)
      - Stieglitz, Elizabeth Stieffel, circa 1942 (Box 17, Folder 223)
      - Stieglitz, Emmeline Obermeyer, circa 1898 (Box 17, Folder 224)
      - Stieglitz, Hedwig Werner, 1895-1906 (Box 17, Folder 225)
      - Stieglitz, Julius, undated (Box 17, Folder 226)
      - Stieglitz, Leopold, circa 1900-1934 (Box 17, Folder 227)
      - Straus, Flora Stieglitz, circa 1905 (Box 17, Folder 228)
    - Groups
      - Edward and Hedwig Werner Stieglitz, circa 1862 (Box 17, Folder 229)
      - Hedwig Werner Stieglitz, with children and grandchildren, 1867-1910 (Box 17, Folder 230)
      - Agnes and Selma Stieglitz playing cards with Eugene Small, circa 1876 [copy of photograph], undated (Box 17, Folder 231)
      - Unidentified trio posed in automobile (tintype), circa 1876 (Box 17, Folder 232)
      - Edward Stieglitz with Agnes and Selma (tintype), circa 1877 (Box 17, Folder 233)
      - Edward, Hedwig and Alfred Stieglitz, with Rosa Werner, Lake George (tintype), circa 1878 (Box 17, Folder 234)
      - Alfred, Leo, and Julius Stieglitz with friends, Bozen (Tyrol), circa 1882 (Box 17, Folder 235)
      - Edward, Alfred, Leo, and Julius Stieglitz, Berlin, circa 1883 (Box 17, Folder 236)
      - Stieglitz family and friends in Europe, circa 1885 (Box 17, Folder 237)
      - Agnes and Selma Stieglitz, circa 1885 (Box 17, Folder 238)
      - Flora, Agnes, and Selma Stieglitz, circa 1885 (Box 17, Folder 239)
      - Group of women, including Fanny Rosenstein, circa 1885 (Box 17, Folder 240)
      - Stieglitz and Foord sisters, on porch at Oaklawn, circa 1887 (Box 17, Folder 241)
      - Agnes and Selma Stieglitz, with Emmeline Obermeyer, circa 1892 (Box 17, Folder 242)
      - Anna Stieffel Stieglitz with Hedwig, 1896 (Box 17, Folder 243)
      - Selma Stieglitz Schubart with William Howard, 1897?
      - Stieglitz grandchildren at Oaklawn, 1896-1907 (Box 17, Folder 244)
      - Elizabeth Stieffel Stieglitz with Flora, 1896 (Box 17, Folder 245)
      - Stieglitz family at Oaklawn, circa 1900
      - Alfred and Leopold Stieglitz, with Hugh Grant Straus, circa 1945 (Box 17, Folder 246)
    - Miscellaneous
      Includes images of Oaklawn and "The Hill" (across the road from Oaklawn), Lake George, NY
      - Alfred Stieglitz's toy horses (tintype), circa 1873-1875 (Box 17, Folder 247)
      - Stieglitz family horse and carriage, circa 1900 (lantern slide), circa 1920 (Box 17, Folder 248)
      - Bowling club beefsteak party, 1893
        Existence and Location of Originals
        Stored in: Oversize, box 18, folder 254
      - Oaklawn and "The Hill", circa 1900 (Box 17, Folder 249)
      - Oaklawn, negatives by Julius Stieglitz, with later prints, circa 1910, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 250)
      - Oaklawn and "The Hill," aerial view, circa 1945
  - Ephemera
    - Theatre programs [in German], 1866
- Oversize, 1878-1979; 0.25; (2 boxes)
  - Photograph album with prints of Stieglitz family members and famous works of art (in Series I), undated (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Calendar with print of AS photograph: "The Terminal" (in Series II), 1979 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Diplomas and awards (in Series III), 1878-1912 (Box 9, Folder 142)
    Includes: Medical degree from the University Ruperto-Carola (1891); Attendance awards from the Grammar School for Boys (1878-79); Declaration of election as Fellow of the New York Academy of Medicine (1912)
  - "Dinner for Dr. Leopold Stieglitz tendered by his friends on his seventy-fifth birthday at the Lotos Club" (in Series V), 1942 May 26 (Box 18, Folder 180)
    Same image as in Series I, Box 1, folder 26
  - Alfred Stieglitz (in Series VII), circa 1894 (Box 18, Folder 251)
  - Selma Stieglitz Schubart with William Howard (in Series VII), 1897? (Box 18, Folder 252)
  - Bowling club beefsteak party (in Series VII), 1893 (Box 18, Folder 253)
  - Stieglitz family at Oaklawn (in Series VII), circa 1900 (Box 18, Folder 254)
  - Oaklawn and "The Hill," aerial view (in Series VII), circa 1945 (Box 18, Folder 255)
  - Theatre programs [in German] (in Series VII), 1866 (Box 18, Folder 256)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 3, folder 67 (Box 10, Folder 143)
  - Box 3, folder 68 (Box 10, Folder 144)
  - Box 3, folder 75 (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Box 3, folder 80 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Box 5, folder 121 (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Box 5, folder 122 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Box 1, folder 26 (Box cold storage, Folder 181)
  - Box 1, folder 29 (Box cold storage, Folder 182)
  - Box 1, folder 32 (Box cold storage, Folder 183)
  - Box 1, folder 125 (Box cold storage, Folder 184)